Henry Hill Papers
© 2003 University of Connecticut
Henry Hill Papers.
1805-1962.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Hill, Henry.
2.75 linear feet.
The Hill Papers primarily consist of family correspondence to and from Henry Hill. Other correspondents include his wife, Lucy M.R. Hill, several of their ten children and various family relations. In addition, the collection contains materials pertaining to the business activities of the Hill and Russel families, particularly in regard to the acquisition of property.
MSS20000122
Biography
Henry Hill was born in Guilford, Connecticut, on 4 July 1778. In 1808 he was appointed by President Thomas Jefferson as U.S. Consul to the port of San Salvador (Bahia), Brazil. He served until 1819, when he resigned because of failing health and moved to a large plantation, Columbiano, some distance from Bahia. He and his family lived there for fourteen years before returning to the United States in 1833. Hill resided in Buffalo, New York, until his death on 24 July 1841.
According to the "Brief Historical Sketch of the American Consulate in Bahia" [Correspondence: Hill, Henry], Henry Hill remained as Consul at Bahia until 11 July 1818, when he was named Consul at Rio de Janeiro, confirmed by the Senate on 30 November 1818. He continued to be active in business at Rio de Janeiro, as he had previously been at Bahia, until May 1821, at which time he left for the United States.
Scope and Content
The Hill Papers primarily consist of family correspondence to and from Henry Hill. Other correspondents include his wife, Lucy M.R. Hill, several of their ten children and various family relations. In addition, the collection contains materials pertaining to the business activities of the Hill and Russel families, particularly in regard to the acquisition of property. Several members of the Hill and Russel families were interested in genealogy. [Genealogical report is not available electronically because of software incompatability, please contact Archives & Special Collections if you would like a copy.]
Note: Samuel Russel, Henry Hill's father-in- law, spells his name with one "l". Others, and in later generations members of the family, spell it "Russell". Materials in the "Unknown" correspondence files consist of letter fragments, poems, two items in German and a letter in Spanish for which authorship could not be determined.
Organization
Series I: Publications (undated, 1835-1962) includes genealogical excerpts from several family members, a published collection of articles written by Leander Stratton, Obituaries and a plan for a bank, presumably drafted by Henry Hill.
Series II: Correspondence (undated, 1805-1962) contains correspondence to and from various members of the Hill and Russel extended families. The materials are arranged by correspondent.
Series III: Other Documents (undated, 1812-1868) includes published and manuscript government, Financial, and Legal documents relating to the interests of Henry Hill and Samuel Russel.
Series IV: Special Format Materials (undated) contains needlework created by members of the Hill family, photographs, pieces of jewelry and a scabbard and Henry Hill's sword.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a several collections pertaining to Latin America and Hispanic History and Culture. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
The materials have been filed by subject. Newspaper clippings have been photocopied. Several family members have made transcriptions of letters over the years. If the original is not in the collection, the transcription has been retained and filed as if it were the original. All duplicates and newspaper clippings have been returned to the donor.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Organizations:
Family Names:
Hill family.; Russel family.
Places:
Brazil.
Subjects:
Diplomatic and consular service, American.; Diplomats--United States--Biography.; United States--Foreign relations--Brazil.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Financial Records.; Legal Records.
Occupations:
U.S. Consul to Brazil.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Archives & Special Collections in November 2000 by Hill Bullard.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Publications, 1835-1962
  - Antler, 1936 (Box 1:1)
  - Articles, 1930-1962 (Box 1:2)
  - Genealogical extracts, undated, 1918-1951 (Box 1:3)
  - "Prospective plan for a Bank...", 1835 (Box 1:4)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1805-1962
  - Brown, Wesley, 1878 (Box 1:5)
  - Business Correspondence, undated, 1808-1840 (Box 1:6)
  - Business Correspondence, 1808-1819 (Box 2:45)
  - Charles Reicke and Bros., 1862 (Box 1:7)
  - Family genealogical correspondence, 1883-1962 (Box 1:8)
  - Family genealogical correspondence, undated (Box 2:46)
  - Bainbridge, Commodore, 1812 (Box 3:58)
  - Bates, Thomas, undated, 1838 (Box 1:9)
  - Elliot, Charles, 1871 (Box 1:10)
  - Elliott, Henry H., 1831 (Box 1:11)
  - Foster, Arch., 1839-1845 (Box 1:12)
  - Hill, Benjamin, 1834 (Box 1:13)
  - Hill, Edward R., undated (Box 1:14)
  - Hill, George, 1871 (Box 1:15)
  - Hill, Henry, Sr., 1827 (Box 1:16)
  - Hill, Henry, undated (Box 1:17)
  - Hill, Henry, 1805-1819 (Box 1:18)
  - Hill, Henry, 1812-1834 (Box 2:47)
  - Hill, Henry, 1833-1839 (Box 1:19)
  - Hill, Henry Marcus, 1862 (Box 1:20)
  - Hill, Leah, 1819 (Box 2:48)
  - Hill, Lucy M. Russel, undated, 1810-1860 (Box 1:21)
  - Hill, Lucy M. R., 1826-1828 (Box 2:49)
  - Hill, Mary Georgiana, 1870 (Box 1:22)
  - Hill, Sarah R., 1833 (Box 2:50)
  - Introduction to Washington Irving, 1837 (Box 1:23)
  - Jacobs, Oliver, undated (Box 1:24)
  - Lawler, V. W., 1867 (Box 1:25)
  - Lyon, Ann, 1833 (Box 1:26)
  - Mitchell, M.A., 18?? [1810] (Box 1:27)
  - Pinneo, Bazaleel, 1831 (Box 1:28)
  - Pinneo, Leah H., 1830 (Box 2:51)
  - Russel, Samuel, undated, 1811-1834 (Box 1:29)
  - Russel, Samuel, 1828-1831 (Box 2:52)
  - Russell, Sarah, undated (Box 2:53)
  - Russell, Sarah J., 1851 (Box 1:30)
  - Stratton, C., 1898 (Box 1:31)
  - Stratton, Cora and Stratton, Nettie, undated (Box 1:32)
  - Stratton, Harriet (Hattie) R., 1921 (Box 1:33)
  - Stratton, Henry Hill, undated (Box 1:34)
  - Stratton, Lorenzo, 1866 (Box 1:35)
  - Tomlinson, Sarah H., 1830-1835 (Box 1:36)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 1:37)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 2:54)
  - Williams, D.W., 1858 (Box 1:38)
  - Williams, Harriet W., undated, 1830-1876 (Box 1:39)
- Series III: Other Documents, 1812-1868
  - Financial, undated, 1834 (Box 2:55)
  - Financial, undated, 1835-1840 (Box 1:40)
  - Government, 1815, 1868 (Box 2:56)
  - Government, undated, 1831 (Box 1:41)
  - Journal of a Voyage to Columbiano, undated (Box 1:42)
  - Legal, 1812, 1837 (Box 2:57)
  - Legal, 1836 (Box 1:43)
- Series IV: Special Format Materials, undated
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1:44)
  - Linen cross-stitch sampler, undated (Box 3)
  - Embroidered napkins, undated (Box 3)
  - Linen with Portuguese lace, undated (Box 3)
  - Pieces and designs for jewelry, undated (Box 3)
  - Pieces of metal scabbard (presumably for sword), undated (Box 3)
  - Sword, undated (Box Roll)